one of the most common questions that I
receive from friends and family members
and just beginner lifters who are new to
my blog is you know where do I start
okay I want to start working out I want
to embark on a on a training regimen and
and where do I begin and I've never
really addressed this on my blog so I
wanted to film a video and and discuss
this this question because it's really
really important so rarely do I just say
go find a personal trainer uh because I
don't know if that trainer is
experienced and and you know if you've
been to a lot of commercial gyms a lot
of personal trainers they don't really
know what they're doing they they'll
they'll they'll start people off right
away you know on the Smith machine or or
they'll just put a barbell on someone's
back and they're not ready for load you
really need to master body weight before
you add external loading and you need to
be performing the movements correctly
um with with proper range of motion and
and you know proper movement and and
stability at some places and Mobility
other places so in this video I'm going
to go over the three what I feel are the
three most important lower body
movements that you need to master right
off the bat and once you master these
then you add load but take a couple
weeks take two three four weeks if you
need to and just practice these
movements over and over get it to where
they're down pat to where they feel out
of automatic and then start adding load
but it's really really critical that you
do this because this provides the
foundation your form is the base you
know it's the foundation of everything
and you build upon that if you start
right off the bat and learn the wrong
way you're setting yourself up for
problems down the road so these three
movements are the boss squat the RDL and
the glute bridge and the RDL stands for
Romanian deop you could also call it a
hip hinge so I'm going to show you the
box squat the hip hinge and the glute
Bridge pattern and I'm going to I'm
going to teach you good form and I'm
going to show you how people typically
screw them up okay so first movement box
squat you are going to find a a a chair
or a a small table or or a stool or
something and or or a a a couch whatever
but just something to we um and and you
might need to have it higher some people
can have it lower but the basic premise
is this is going to help teach you how
to sit back you know most people if I
just say squat they'll go like this and
they shift forward they Bend at the
knees and they do this because they
don't have good posture chain strength
when you've got strong hips you use them
you sit back and you absorb the load
with your hips but the hips get weak
over time people lose strength in their
hips and so they resort to quad dominant
strategies that's why most people use
their quads too much and they don't use
their hips enough and that sets you up
for problems so this is why the Box
Squad is so useful it teaches you how to
sit back now here are the things you
need to know about the box squat you're
going to take a wide stance you can turn
the feet out most people prefer about
around a 30° flare but some people still
like to feet keep the feet straight and
that's okay some people flare more
that's okay too I prefer around a 30°
flare okay I am going to put my arms in
the mummy position and I am going to sit
sit back these are shorts are tight so
I'm going to sit
back come up okay this is how the
movement
looks now let me break it down for
you if you notice my tibia this bone
right here stays pretty vertical meaning
if you drew a line it go straight up
through the ceiling um my knees will
stay out they track over my
toes all right I sit back I don't plop I
keep my chest up I lean in and as I come
up I squeeze the glutes forward and I
stay with the weight on my heels so the
common errors with this you will find
that most
people will want to bend forward too
much at the knees their knees will track
very far forward and they won't keep
this vertical Tippy they won't be able
to sit back and so you'll say sit back
and they'll go like this and they
they'll stay pretty upright because
they're trying to use their quads
they're not trying to use their hips um
the other thing people do is you'll see
they'll they'll come up onto their toes
and that's again a strategy to use more
quad and probably the the most common
thing is their knees will cave in and
especially women because women are
trying to be ladies you know they want
to sit like a lady you don't ever see
women sit down like this they sit down
like this you know and and try and cover
up and this this leads to faulty
movement patterns over time this is
called vus collapse it can lead to knee
problems over time so let me do this
from the side
view wide stance I'm put weights on my
heels okay I sit back I keep my knees
out okay I come up squeeze the glutes
this is what it looks like just like
this and that's got to become automatic
over time it takes time you know you
might not be able at first you might
only be able to go to here you know and
then over time you can start sitting
back more and more eventually you'll get
to where you can sit back all the way
you know you'll feel kind of a stretch
and you'll feel the load in the hips
come up squeeze the glutes but um you
don't want to plop like this a lot of
times you'll see people come back come
back and go you don't want to plop sit
down comfortably and come up all right
so that's the Box squat once you get
good at this exercise now you can just
put a dumbbell right underneath your
chin and load it up just like
this but that that's that's after you've
gotten good with body weight now you can
add load but don't add load until you've
mastered the body weight um
pattern okay now let me go over the RDL
or the hip
hinge this is an a a easy movement in
terms of strength it doesn't require a
lot of strength but it requires motor
control you need to know where to move
and where not to move so if you watch
the way most people pick something up
off the ground they'll kind of go like
this and pick it up and that's a very
economical way to pick something off the
ground you're going to use a combination
of hip flexion Lumbar and thoric spine
flexion and pick something off the
ground but in weightlifting we don't
want to move that way we want to teach
our body to stabilize the spine and the
movement to occur around the hips so
with the RDL pattern start out with your
hands on the front of your thighs okay
don't set up like a squat with a wide
stance get a narrow stance with your
feet Straight Ahead okay hands on the
front of the
thighs and I am just going to sit back
imagine someone has a rope around your
waist and they're pulling back they're
they pull back on that rope you sit back
and notice my head stays in line I'm not
going like this and hyperextending my
head my neck so this is what the RDL
pattern looks
like all right let me break this down so
a lot of
beginners they will
round they will move the knees forward
too much they will try and squat it's
not a squat the hips stay high or they
would will keep the legs straight and
just go like this you want if this is
why you put the hands on the on the on
the thighs because if you had a barbell
or a dumbbell it would skim your body so
the knees stay soft meaning they're not
straight like this and they will bend
but you're limiting how much forward
knee displacement you have
here so
again weight is on the heels okay I keep
my head in n NE Al soone has a rope
around my hips and they're pulling back
so I sit back sit back the knees Bend
but I'm sitting back while my hands just
skim down my legs okay I get a big
stretch in my
hamstrings I reverse now I can't go any
deeper because if I went deeper I would
lose this arch in my back I would have
to go like this so this is as deep as I
can go and now I reverse the movement
and I come up and now I squeeze my
glutes I don't stop here I pushed those
hips forward with my glutes so that's
the hip hinge pattern once you get
proficient with body weight once this
feels natural for you now you can hold
on to dumbbells and do the same thing or
a barbell but master that pattern first
all right and now the third movement is
the glute bridge now the glute
bridge this looks like a simple movement
just like the others I'm just going
to squeeze my
glutes raise my hips into the air the
problem is most people do this movement
incorrectly most people you poke their
glutes and they're not turning on that
much most people you'll feel their
hamstrings and their low back and you
feel the tension coming from their their
hammies and their low back you need to
feel the the hammies and the the low
back muscles you'll feel them but they
won't be turned on maximally the glute
should be turned on maximally and so
what you'll find is a lot of beginners
they will come up like this and you'll
look and they're they're arching this
way kind of their chest comes up in
their if you were to feel their lumbar
spine arches this way they hyperextend
their lumbar spine you don't want that
you want this core staying stable the
whole time the core remains stable the
glutes push the hips
up okay and over time like my glutes
right now Rock Solid
so you want to feel the glutes pushing
the hips
upwards just like that and once you get
good at this movement now you can put a
dumbbell in your lap just like
this okay but make sure you do it right
make sure you lay down the proper
Foundation learn how to do these
movements properly with body weight and
then slowly start adding load over time
you've got all the Time in the World to
get strong and add weight and you know
if you've been f in this blog for a
while you know that I've got you know
females using 315 lbs for hip thrust and
you know girls deadlifting 275 lbs and
girls doing box squats with 135 lbs but
they all started off mastering their
body weight first and so lay the proper
foundation and then go from there